Clayton Seitz

cwseitz@iu.edu cwseitz.github.io

PERSONAL STATEMENT

I maintain a diverse academic background and specialize in the development of probabilistic models, including deep generative models, for biological discovery and computer vision. I have previously used cutting-edge modeling techniques to study the interaction of epigenetic proteins with nucleosome nanodomains and validated findings experimentally using super-resolution fluorescence microscopy.

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosopy, Physics

Indiana University, Indianapolis, IN

Thesis: Advancing super-resolution microscopy for quantitative in-vivo imaging of chromatin nanodomains

Master of Science, Biophysics

University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, 2021

Thesis: Stable cell assembly formation in excitatory-inhibitory neural networks

Bachelor of Science, Physics, Magna cum laude

Indiana University, Indianapolis, IN, 2019

Minor: Mathematics

Bachelor of Science, Informatics, Magna cum laude

Luddy School of Informatics, Computing, and Engineering, Indiana University Bloomington, 2019

Concentration: Mathematics

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Graduate Research Assistant

2022-Present

Indiana University, Indianapolis, IN

- Design deep generative models for enhancing super-resolution fluorescence microscopy
- Investigate the impact of point mutations within epigenetic proteins on their structure using AlphaFold
- Investigate the impact of point mutations of epigenetic proteins on the structure of nucleosome nanodomains and complement experimental data with molecular dynamics simulations

Graduate Trainee

2020-2022

University of Chicago, Chicago, IL

- Utilize fluorescence microscopy to measure temporal dynamics of calcium concentration in single cells
- Generate Monte Carlo simulations of spiking neural networks to relate network architecture to spiking dynamics

Undergraduate Research Assistant

2019-2020

Indiana University, Indianapolis, IN

• Develop an image processing package in Python for processing large volumes of images generated by fluorescence microscopy

• Utilize time-correlated single photon counting (TCSPC) to characterize the sub-Poissonian emission of organic quantum dots dispersed in a thin film of poly-methyl methacrylate (PMMA)

AWARDS

NIH Graduate Training Fellowship University of Chicago, Chicago, IL 2020

Travel Award and Lightning Talk Invitation Physical Sciences in Oncology - Minneapolis, MN 2019

Hudson and Holland Scholarship for Diversity and Inclusion

2013-2017

Indiana University, Bloomington, IN

Founders Scholar

2013-2017

Indiana University, Bloomington, IN

Cigital Scholarship

2016-2017

Indiana University, Bloomington, IN

PUBLICATIONS Clayton Seitz[†], Donghong Fu[†], Mengyuan Liu, Hailan Ma, and Jing Liu. BRD4 phosphorylation regulates the structure of chromatin nanodomains. In Review. 2024

> Clayton Seitz and Jing Liu. Uncertainty-aware localization microscopy by variational diffusion. In Review. 2024

> Maelle Locatelli[†], Josh Lawrimore[†], Hua Lin[†], Sarvath Sanaullah, Clayton Seitz, Dave Segall, Paul Kefer, Salvador Moreno Naike, Benton Lietz, Rebecca Anderson, Julia Holmes, Chongli Yuan, George Holzwarth, Bloom Kerry, Jing Liu, Keith D Bonin, Pierre-Alexandre Vidi. DNA damage reduces heterogeneity and coherence of chromatin motions. PNAS 12 July 2022; 119 (29): 1-11

> Mengdi Zhang, Clayton Seitz, Garrick Chang, Fadil Iqbal, Hua Lin, and Jing Liu A guide for single-particle chromatin tracking in live cell nuclei. Cell Biology International 15 January 2022; 46 (5): 683-700

> Wenting Wu, Farooq Syed, Edward Simpson, Chih-Chun Lee, Jing Liu, Garrick Chang, Chuanpeng Dong, Clayton Seitz, Decio L. Eizirik, Raghavendra G. Mirmira, Yunlong Liu, Carmella Evans-Molina; Impact of Proinflammatory Cytokines on Alternative Splicing Patterns in Human Islets. Diabetes 25 October 2021; 71 (1): 116 - 127

> Clayton Seitz, Hailan Ma, and Jing Liu. Bayesian analysis of GBP5 transcriptional bursts. Biophysical Society Annual Conference 2022

> Clayton Seitz, Hua Lin, Keith Bonin, Pierre-Alexandre Vidi, and Jing Liu. Quantifying the spatiotemporal dynamics of dUTP labeled chromatin during the DNA damage response. Biophysical Society Annual Conference 2020

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages & Software: Python, R, PyTorch, C/C++, Git, LaTeX, Bash, HPCs/SLURM